Okay. המוכר זיתיו לעצים ועשו פחות מרביעית לסאה הרי אלו של בעל
הזיתים. Ha-mokher zeito le-etzim ve-asu pahot me-revi’it le-se’ah harei elu shel ba’al
ha-zeitim.
If I sell olive trees to be used for wood
and nonetheless it's still olive trees they have olives on them, ועשו
פחות מרביעית לסאה ve-asu pahot me-revi’it le-se’ah and they have a certain
a very low amount of oil, less than a quarter of a
log for a סאה's se’ah worth of
field. סאה Se’ah I think is בית סאה beit se’ah I think.
That's the amount of זיתים zeitim or is it בית סאה? beit
se’ah? I'm not sure. Anyway, anyway, it's a very, very low amount
of oil for the olives.
This just means
not even a quarter log, not even a רביעית revi'it quarter log.
Okay, yeah. And then it's an עשירית asirit or something? Okay anyway,
הרי אלו של
בעל הזיתים.
Harei elu
shel ba’al ha-zeitim. And even though I the owner of the זיתים
zeitim now... oh, sorry... Okay. The person who bought the זיתים... zeitim...
the זיתים... zeitim... the trees... the person who bought the olive trees
to use them for wood, even though I only bought them for
wood, I still have the rights to the זיתים zeitim if it's
a very low... I still have the rights to the olives themselves
and their oil they produce if they produce a very low amount
of oil.
Because presumably the person who owned who planted the זיתים zeitim and
sold them to me didn't care about that little of little amount
of oil.
That's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say in a moment.
הזיתים Ha-zeitim עשו רביעית לסאה asu revi’it le-se’ah but if they do
make that minimum amount, זה אומר זיתי גדלו zeh omer zeitai gadlu
וזה אומר ארצי גדלה. ve-zeh omer artzi gadla.
So one argues, the person who bought the זיתים zeitim who bought
the trees argues, 'These are my trees, they produced that oil, they
should be mine.'
The other one says, 'No, it's my land, my land has all
the various minerals in the soil, that's what actually produced this oil
properly and so I should own the oil.' יחלוקו. Yahalloku.
So just like we saw earlier in previous cases, what happens here
when both make a good claim? They split. שטף נהר זיתיו ונתנם
לתוך שדה חבירו. Shataph nahar zeitav u-netanam le-tokh sadeh havero.
There's a flood and I have these זיתים, zeitim, I have these
olive trees and they get moved by a flood into somebody else's
field. ונתנם לתוך שדה חבירו, U-netanam le-tokh sadeh havero, זה אומר זיתי
גדלו וזה אומר ארצי גדלה יחלוקו.
zeh omer zeitai gadlu ve-zeh omer
artzi gadla yahalloku. Same issue.
I can claim that even though they're not in my field anymore,
these are my trees, they're the ones that produce the oil, so
the oil should be mine. And the person in whose field the
trees are now planted because there was this ridiculous flood that moved
these trees can claim, 'No, it's my field and the quality of
my soil that grew these olives and that developed this oil and
so this is my oil.' And so they split. גמרא. Gemara.
He says it was a tree.
Is it possible that just the olives, in some...
what do you mean?
Just the olives, not the whole tree?
שטף נהר זיתיו.
Shataph nahar zeitav.
No, it's the tree.
Yeah, this dialect uses consistently when it wants to mean a certain
kind of tree, it says the fruit it produces. It's true anyway
I think like the תמר. tamar. Okay.
But there's no issue about how long after the flood these claims
are coming?
There is exactly an issue of how long after the flood these
claims are coming because we're going to have to deal with ערלה.
orlah.
So, and that's the next סוגיא. sugya. So, good question. היכי דמי?
Heikhi dami?
So what are we talking about here in the first case? אי
דאמר ליה קוץ לאלתר. Ei de-amar lei kotz le-altar. If it's the
first case, remember, was the one where I bought somebody has olive
trees planted in their field and I buy them. So then, and
then we have a certain amount... I buy them for wood. And
how do we split the oil that gets produced anyway? היכי דמי?
Heikhi dami? אי דאמר ליה קוץ לאלתר. Ei de-amar lei kotz le-altar.
If it's that we made the deal that I say, 'Okay, you
buy the trees, cut them right now,' אפילו פחות מרביעית נמי לבעל
הקרקע. afilu pahot me-revi’it nami le-ba’al ha-karka.
Even the smallest amount of oil that's there that gets produced later
on should also be לבעל הקרקע le-ba’al ha-karka because this is דוקא
davka for the firewood and so we don't and so I do
care about the oil, and so if I'm telling you, 'Chop the
wood now,' and so any amount of oil should be mine if
we made the deal that you're buying the firewood now. אי דאמר
ליה כל אימת דבעית קוץ, Ei de-amar lei kol eimat de-ba’it kotz,
אפילו רביעית נמי לבעל הזיתים. afilu revi’it nami le-ba’al ha-zeitim. But if
I say, 'Okay, whenever you want, come chop this firewood, these trees
are yours for firewood,' I'm not really making a condition that these
trees are your for firewood, I'm saying these trees are yours to
deal with and so any amount of oil should also be yours,
the person who bought the trees, not the person who owns the
field.
How would a person actually make the difference? If you're, you know,
presumably at least in my way of generalizing these transactions, you buy
the asset and all rights to it, you know what I mean?
Intellectual property, da-da-da-da-da.
So buying a tree is a special kind of deal where there's
various rules about buying a tree, especially for wood, because like I
might allow you to buy this tree for wood, but what does
that mean? Can I does that mean that I can totally uproot
the tree? Can I hurt your land? Can I plant a different
kind of tree on this land? Do I own this land? No,
I bought the tree. Do I buy am I buying real estate?
It's מחובר לקרקע, m'chubar l'karka, it should be like קרקע. karka. It's
connected to the ground so I should be treating it like buying
land but I don't. The tree is a weird case which is
why even though we assume that it should be I buy this
and all the rights attend to it, it's different because it's a
tree on land. And so I can't...
but you
can buy the
fruit separate from the tree.
Yeah
that's kind of like arbitrary in some way. You know what I
mean? You could have just said you buy the tree you get
the tree and anything that's on it. I mean like I'm buying
the wood, the wood has stuff on it. You know what I
mean?
What if there was oil in the land?
In the land?
I'm not buying the land, I'm just buying the tree. Now there's
a tree and anything that's on it. No there's like if I
buy a לולב lulav that has like little berries they'd say oh
I just want the לולב lulav but you
got to give back the berries, you know? I think this makes
actually, I think this actually makes a lot of sense. If I
rent a, if I buy a vineyard and I say I'm going
to buy this tract, I'm going to press myself, I'm going to
make a kosher, I'm going to some vineyard in Napa or wherever.
You can see I'm from California so I think Napa, somebody else
might think of some other valley. I go to Napa, I say
this tract of vines I'm going to buy this, I'm going to
make mines. Doesn't mean that I can go and I can start
making grafts of different of different species of grapes onto these vines
because next year you're going to grow, you're going to grow another
batch of grapes onto this thing. When I'm dealing with plants and
I don't own the land
then
my rights to this land are separate. My rights to this tree
are separate from whatever else might be going on here.
But if you're buying it for wood presumably they're going to be
cut down. What's a little bit of... they're cut down with whatever's
on them.
They're cut down with a certain amount and then we're saying לאו
דוקא. lav davka. Okay, we got to go on. Okay we said
in one case it's one way, in one case it's the other
way, not like the משנה, Mishnah, לא צריכא דאמר ליה סתמא. lo
tzricha d'amar lei stama. So the משנה Mishnah is actually necessary to
teach the case where we just said I'm buying these for wood,
not now, not later, and we don't say when. And so there's
some assumptions that aren't made explicit and so thus the rule has
to be יחלוקו yachloku depending on the, has to be that they
split it depending on the amount of oil that's produced. פחות מרבי
לא קפדי אינשי, pachot mirvi lo kapdei inshi, less than a רביעית,
revi'it, less than the small amount of oil the person who owned
the land and planted the trees and sold the trees doesn't really
care. רבי revi kapdei inshi, but more than that amount people do
care about the oil that was produced and they've lost by selling
the trees for wood and so they have the right, the rights
to parts of it. אמר רבי שמעון בן פזי ורביעית שאמרו חוץ
מן ההוצאה. Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Pazi v'revi'it she'amru chutz min ha'hotza'ah.
But this רביעית revi'it is actually measured in, measured monetarily and it's
less than the amount, it's net, yeah, it's net רביעית revi'it less
than the amount that it costs to actually pick and press the
oil. שטפה נהר זיתיו, Shtafas nahar zeisav, so now we're moving on
to the next part of the משנה Mishnah which is the strange
case of the tree being carried off by a flood. שטפה נהר
זיתיו אמר עולא אמר ריש לקיש לא שנו אלא שנעקר בגושם ולאחר
שלש אבל בתוך שלש הכל לבעל הזיתים ואמרי ליה אי את נטעת
בתוך שלש מי הוה אכל. Shtafas nahar zeisav amar Ulla amar Reish
Lakish lo shanu ela shenekar b'gusham u'le'achar shalosh aval betoch shalosh hakol
le'ba'al hazeisim v'amrei lei i at natata betoch shalosh mi hava achal.
It's a strange place to stop. Anyway. עולא Ulla says in the
name of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish this actually only applies when the
trees are taken away with some pack of soil around the bottom.
Why? רש"י Rashi will explain that it's necessary and לאחר שלש le'achar
shalosh after three years. Why are we dealing with three years? רש"י
Rashi explains that and everybody else agrees that this has to do
with ערלה. orlah. ערלה orlah is the rule that a tree that's
plant, that when a tree is planted for the first three years
you can't do anything with the fruit. After three years you can
do with the fruit. And so it matters that this tree took
the land with it, so כאילו ke'ilu there's no issue of ערלה
orlah on this tree itself. But בתוך שלש betoch shalosh we have
to deal with what would I have done, what I would have
done with this land where this tree is currently planted that I
didn't put there, that the flood put there, what I would have
done with it in those first three years. If I planted another
tree I wouldn't have had access to those fruits. But this tree
is not ערלה orlah because it was נעקר בגושם. ne'ekar b'gusham. It
has the land that it brought with it. So it is not
an ערלה orlah tree in a place where there would be an
ערלה orlah tree and so my arguments back and forth between the
בעל הקרקע, ba'al hakarka, the owner of the land where the tree
has now been planted by the flood, and the person who owned
the tree itself has to do with what would have happened בתוך
שלש betoch shalosh and אחר שלש. achar shalosh.
I don't understand. So if I have a fifty year old tree
and a flood moves it into your field and it still has
soil I put it in mine and there's no ערלה? orlah?
From this I would have to say yes.
That's very interesting. I wouldn't have thought that.
Me neither. And so I might be wrong.
Okay, but
from this, from this it's... and when I was in orchards in
the summer they told us that to transplant a tree you had
to make sure that it's transplanted with a certain amount...
right, that's this, that's for
ערלה orlah purposes, that's this גוש.
gush.
Good gardening purposes, but yes.
But
they explicitly said for ערלה.
orlah. Yeah.
Okay, I'll go... okay, so לאחר שלש. le'achar shalosh. So we can
only say this rule about
יחלוקו yachloku after three years have passed. אבל בתוך שלש Aval betoch
shalosh we say, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says, really I the owner
of the tree should have the rights to all of the fruits.
Why? דאמר ליה אי את נטעת בתוך שלש, D'amar lei i at
natata betoch shalosh, if you the owner of the field had planted
your own olive tree here within the first three years you wouldn't
have had any access to the fruits anyway because it would have
been ערלה. orlah. This, my tree, magically here without
ערלה, orlah, magically... Exactly. That's exactly the
argument of it. However, ולימא ליה ve-leimal but the owner of
the
field can say back אי אנא נטעי ואחר שלוש שנים הוה אכילנא
ליה לכוליה. ee ana nataie ve-acher shalosh shanim hava achilna leih le-chuleih.
What are you talking about? After three years, we're going to split
this? But
if I'd planted it myself, these would all be mine. So how
can you make the argument that before שלוש shalosh I had to
give all of it to you? We should be splitting it before
שלוש shalosh years as well. השתא קא פגא בהדאי, hashta k'ha paga
behadai,
you should be sharing it right now, when the first three years
that your weird tree is planted in my field.
Why would we be doing that in
the first three years though? Nothing. Oh, no, so, sorry, if the
point of splitting it is that this tree, which was נעקר בגושו,
ne-ekar be-gusho, that it doesn't have the דין din of ערלה. orlah.
So it brought the soil with it to the second field; it
actually doesn't have an ערלה orlah rule on it.
So you
could use it immediately.
The question is we compare this to what I would have done
had I planted my own tree,
which you couldn't have used.
But I couldn't have used it. That's the argument that the בעל
הזיתים, Ba'al Ha-Zeitim, the owner of the trees, should have complete rights
to the fruits in the first three years of it being in
the other person's field. The argument back is that had I, the
owner of the field, planted my own tree here, after three years
it would be entirely mine, and so in the first three years
we should be splitting.
Okay.
And we totally ignore the possibility that the original owner would say,
"I want my trees back. Dig them up and put them back
where they were."
No, that is—that's not addressed in the גמרא. Gemara. The ראשונים Rishonim
bring that up. All of these cases where I'm putting something in
somebody else's field—well,
here the river did it.
Here the river did it, so it's different. Actually, this case, this
case of the זיתים, zeitim, we deal with. Like, "I'm going to
take back my trees," we deal with what do we do about
that case, and we say, "No, you have to leave them there,"
which is a special rule. We'll come to that in a few
minutes. The other cases that we're going to see, the ראשונים Rishonim
address the possibility of what if you came and you planted in
my field, you came and you built in my area? I had
a ruined building here, and you built a new shed. Do you
get to keep that shed? Only if I let you. If I
make you take it away, you have to take it away.
יאוש Ye'ush is usually, you know, שטף נהר, shataf nahar, you know,
somehow this doesn't come into play.
Yeah,
I think it's because קרקע karka so there's no
יאוש. ye'ush.
So, that was the opinion of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish which was
made problematic because there's actually an argument back. So Reish Lakish's opinion
that the דין din of the משנה Mishna יחלוקו, yechaloku, that they
should split the produce only applies after three years, was made problematic
because there's an argument back to that. And so we have a
different opinion. אלא כי אתא רבין אמר ריש לקיש, Ela ki ata
Ravin amar Reish Lakish, we
have—it's still Reish Lakish, a different version of Reish Lakish, it's a
better version of Reish Lakish. לא שנו אלא שנעקרו בגושיהן. Lo shanu
ela she-ne'ekru be-gusheihen. So we said we're dealing with the problem, we're
dealing with what it would have been had it been ערלה, orlah,
even though the tree isn't ערלה. orlah. ובתוך שלוש, U-ve-tok shalosh,
but the דין din of the משנה Mishna that you split only
applies within the first three years when it would have been ערלה
orlah otherwise. אבל לאחר שלוש הכל לבעל הקרקע. Aval le-acher shalosh hakol
le-ba'al ha-karka. That your tree moved into my land, after three years
it's all mine. דאמר ליה אי אנא נטעי, De-amar lei ee ana
nataie,
because the owner of the land will say, "Had I planted my
own tree, לאחר שלוש מי לא הוה אכלנא ליה לכוליה? le-acher shalosh
mi lo hava achilna leih le-chuleih? I don't care that these are
your trees. Had I planted a tree here, these would have been
mine after three years. So after three years, you can go away
now, you're stuck." ולימא ליה ve-leimal
however, the בעל הזיתים Ba'al Ha-Zeitim can say back—the גמרא Gemara raises
a problem with this point—אי את נטעת בתוך שלוש לא הוה אכלת.
ee at natat be-tok shalosh lo hava achalt. השתא קא פגא בהדאי.
Hashta k'ha paga behadai. Is the first three
years—not a problem with it, it's actually the point of the משנה,
Mishna, which is that בתוך שלוש be-tok shalosh we split. And so
that's because of the second argument, that it's like in your first
three years of planting your own tree, you would have to split
the fruit—or you wouldn't have to do anything with the fruit. And
so now because you have a special new tree in your field
that doesn't have ערלה orlah rules applying to it, we should be
splitting it. And so that's why the דין din of the משנה
Mishna comes through, משום דאמר ליה אי אנא נטעי הוה קטיני וזרענא
תחותייהו סילקא וירקא. mishum de-amar lei ee ana nataie hava katini ve-zar'ana
techoteihu silka ve-yarka.
I have a special—I have a special right, right, I have a
special right to this stuff because if I planted my own tree
even in the first three years, they wouldn't have been that big,
they wouldn't have had that much shade, says רש"י, Rashi, and so
I could have planted other things underneath them. So in the first
three years they're slightly different, and so they end up splitting. In
the first three years there's arguments on both sides, so we end
up splitting. תנא, Tana, a new case,
not an easy one.
No, sorry, this is the same that we just talked about, this
is what if I want to take the tree back. אמר הלה
זיתיי אני נוטל. Amar hala zeitai ani motel. I'm going to go
take back my tree. My tree moved into your field, I want
it back. אין שומעין לו. Ein shomin lo. We say we don't
listen to that person. You're stuck. The tree moved, the river moved
your tree. We have to you have to leave it there. Why?
אמאי טעמא? Amai ta'ama? אמר רבי יוחנן משום ישוב ארץ ישראל. Amar
Rabbi Yochanan mishum yishuv Eretz Yisrael.
Because we have a concern we have a thing that we want
to do we want to build up ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
so the fact that there's a tree in a different place is
great and so we want the tree to stay in its place.
Wait a minute if he's building up ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael then
your part your field is growing and mine isn't. I mean it
goes both ways.
It goes both ways but you're going to plant another tree. More
trees!
You're going to plant another tree!
Yeah but I wasn't going to plant a tree here to begin
with but now there's a new tree here. We say that's ישוב
ארץ ישראל. yishuv Eretz Yisrael. אמר רבי ירמיה כגון דאדרי חברה. Amar
Rabbi Yirmiya kegon de'adrei chavra. רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya says that's a
great explanation. This kind of explanation we need a rabbi for. We
need a this is why you need a teacher because you wouldn't
have thought of that on your own. Otherwise you would have thought
says רש"י Rashi like we see later there's another explanation brought for
the same issue on the top of ק"א ע"ב kuf aleph amud
bet that the reason
אין שומעין לו ein shomin lo is because it actually does damage
but here we say that it's משום ישוב ארץ ישראל. mishum yishuv
Eretz Yisrael. Okay now we have a different rule. תנן התם. Tanan
hatam. We have another משנה mishna somewhere else that's in דמאי Demai
and we're only bringing part of the משנה. mishna. ריפ"א Rippa points
out that the נוסח nusach of the משנה mishna that's brought here
is not precisely the one that we see in דמאי Demai because
here we're going to say it as if it's its own rule.
רבי יהודה אומר המקבל שדה אבותיו מן הנכרי מעשר ונותן לו. Rabbi
Yehuda omer hamikabel sede avotav min hanokhri me'aser venoten lo. One who
is
working
is a sharecropper. This is somebody המקבל hamikabel is somebody who has
who's working a field and they owe a fixed ratio of the
produce of the field to the owner of the field and he
is doing this when a non-Jew is the is the person renting
it to him and it's שדה אבותיו. sede avotav. שדה אבותיו Sede
avotav is his ancestral field. We're going to deal with what שדה
אבותיו sede avotav really means here could be one of two things.
Anyway in the משנה mishna it the תנא קמא tanna kamma talks
about a חוכר choker and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says אף המקבל. af hamikabel. Also the המקבל.
hamikabel. A חוכר choker is somebody that we're going to see in
a minute a חוכר choker is a tenant farmer or something. It's
somebody who farms land and owes a fixed amount of produce. So
it's not a ratio of the produce produced. It's that I owe
you so many bushels of grain over the over the course of
the year to pay to pay you for it. I owe you
that that I owe you. That's what distinguishes the two of them
is whether it's a fixed amount or a ratio of what I
produce. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says אף המקבל. af hamikabel. Here we
just say המקבל. hamikabel. There's no נוסח nusach of the משנה mishna
according to the ריפ"א Rippa who says just
רבי יהודה אומר המקבל. Rabbi Yehuda omer hamikabel. It is the דרך
הגמרא derech hagemara that when the גמרא gemara cites a משנה mishna
from somewhere else and it's only citing part of it it might
change the language more so to to just be able to deal
with what it's talking about which is just worth pointing out here
because we're not going actually look at the משנה. mishna. המקבל שדה
אבותיו מן הנכרי Hamikabel sede avotav min hanokhri someone who is
sharecropping a field from sharecropping his ancestral field from a
non-Jew מעשר ונותן לו. me'aser venoten lo. He has to tithe the
produce all all of the produce and then give the ratio of
that produce to the non-Jew. Why would we have thought otherwise?
It doesn't make sense meaning it's suppose meaning מעשר maaser isn't included
to to diminish your ratio. Is that what we're saying?
מעשר Maaser he's losing out on it maybe maybe
No so what I'm saying meaning like do I give you the
ratio then excluding the מעשר maaser or including the...
No so let's say I have a hundred I have like a
hundred units of grain that I produce I have to take away
ten of them and give them to מעשר maaser and then of
those ninety the ratio I have to give you another twenty percent
so what's point two times nine?
Right so instead of twenty percent of a hundred it's twenty percent
of ninety.
I give you eighteen. I give instead of giving you twenty units
I give you eighteen units but that's the point I'm still losing
out because I had to give the מעשר maaser on the whole
thing. It should have been that I give you that instead of
taking ten away from a hundred and then eighteen away from ninety
I should I should give you your twenty and then I should
give my nine. Why is a non-Jew only someone who Good question.
So
that's the question what do you use why?
Good question.
So that's exactly that's one of the questions that we're going to
deal with what does it mean that we're talking about a a
non-Jew who's has land presumably in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
also why do you have to give tithes for
the
non-Jew has to get tithed produce? So here why does the non-Jew
have to get tithed produce is a question. Why is it in
the case of the sharecropper who's giving a fixed ratio and so
there's a payment and it's not a חוב chov that I'm due?
These are all the questions that we're going to
deal with you don't give the מעשר maaser to the נכרי? nokhri?
No but it's do I have to give the מעשר maaser does
the thing have to be tithed? Can I pay him in טבל?
tevel? Is the question. Can I pay him in untithed produce?
Let's say
can we talk
are we saying ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael?
Okay definitely
it's ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Just
wait patience.
סברוה. Svaruha.
They tried to say they thought about what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
was saying and they thought he meant מאי שדה אבותיו ארץ ישראל?
mai sede avotav Eretz Yisrael? שדה אבותיו Sede avotav means anything in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and so we're dealing with a question of
whether a non-Jew can own land in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and here we say no. anyway אמאי קרי ליה שדה אבותיו? amai
karei lei sede avotav? Why is it called שדה אבותיו? sede avotav?
That's a weird thing to call ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. שדה אברהם
יצחק ויעקב. Sede Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov. אבותיו Avotav like the אבות avot
that it's the field... that belonged to אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Avraham, Yitzchak,
v'Yaakov. וקסבר V'kasavar and he also thinks אין קנין לנוכרי בארץ ישראל
להפקיע מיד מעשר, Ein kinyan l'nochri b'Eretz Yisrael l'hafki'ah mi-yad ma'aser, that
even though this non-Jew is renting it to me in some sense,
he doesn't really own it, I own it or the Jewish people
owns it because it's in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. And so that's
why I have to give מעשר ma'aser on it because there's a
חיוב hiyyuv on מעשר. ma'aser. That שדה אבותיו sde avotav is שדה
אבותיו sde avotav is ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael in this case. And
so this land is חייב hayyav in מעשר. ma'aser.
I never would have thought of that. I would have thought that
if I bought a field, it's not שדה אבותיו. sde avotav.
שדה אבותיו sde avotav is what I actually get
from my mishpacha l'beit avotam as opposed to I buy your field,
it's not שדה אבותיו sde avotav even though it's in ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael.
Yeah, but it's still חייב hayyav in מעשר. ma'aser.
No, but then you could have I mean I would have thought
anyway,
שדה אבותיו sde avotav means any field in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
I thought שדה אבותיו sde avotav means a field I inherited.
So we end up concluding that שדה אבותיו sde avotav really should
be that, but we have to get there first. דקסבר Dik'savar אין
קנין לנוכרי בארץ ישראל להפקיע מיד מעשר, ein kinyan l'nochri b'Eretz Yisrael
l'hafki'ah mi-yad ma'aser, מקבל כחוקר דמי, mikabbel k'hokher dami, and we treat
קבלנו kabblanu where I give you a fixed ratio of the produce
to a חוקר hokher where I give you a fixed amount of
the produce that I have a that there is a certain amount
that I have to give you, I have to give you your
40 bushels whereas a מקבל mikabbel has to give you your 20
percent. מה
חוקר בין עבד בין לא
עבד מיסר מאצמו, Mah hokher,
bein avad bein lo
avad miyassur mi-atzmo,
a חוקר hokher because it's a fixed amount, no matter what I
produce, I have to give your 40 bushels, for
example, דכי פורע חובתו דמי d'khiforei hovato dami
because it's like paying back a debt, and so I'm giving you
something that belongs to you. אף מקבל נמי כי פורע חובתו דמי,
Af mikabbel nami k'forei hovato dami, so first also
according to this interpretation of the משנה Mishnah over there, a מקבל
mikabbel who's giving a fixed ratio is treated as if he's paying
back a debt, which is a little bit of a stretch. מעשר
ונותן לו. Ma'asser v'noten lo. אמר ליה רב כהנא לרב פפא. Amar
lei Rav Kahana l'Rav Pappa.
Let's say that the field produced nothing, a
חוקר hokher would and a מקבל mikabbel would not. Still, which is
why it's difficult to call it a חוב. hov. אמר ליה רב
כהנא לרב פפא. Amar lei Rav Kahana l'Rav Pappa. So we have
a different interpretation. רב כהנא Rav Kahana says to רב פפא, Rav
Pappa, ואמרי לה לרב זביד, v'amri lah l'Rav Zevid, and some people
have the version that he said it to רב זביד, Rav Zevid,
אהא דתניא: A'ha d'tanya: רבי יהודה אומר מקבל שדה אבותיו ממציק נוכרי
מעשר ונותן לו. Rabbi Yehuda omer, mikabbel sde avotav mi-mazzik nochri ma'asser
v'noten lo. Here he's not talking about we have a ברייתא baraita
where we have a similar פנים p'nim to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
but he's not talking about simply that I'm renting from a non-Jew
but that a non-Jew stole this land,
and nonetheless he says מעשר ונותן לו. ma'asser v'noten lo. מאי איריא
מציק? Mai irya mazzik? Why are we talking about somebody who stole
the land? אפילו אין מציק נמי. Afillu ein mazzik nami. אלא לעולם,
Ella l'olam, the משנה Mishnah has to be talking about because the
ברייתא baraita has to fit with the משנה: Mishnah: יש קנין לנוכרי
בארץ ישראל Yesh kinyan l'nochri b'Eretz Yisrael
that a non-Jew can own land in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael להפקיע
מיד מעשר l'hafki'ah mi-yad ma'aser
to take away its sanctity such that the produce of the land
would not be חייב hayyav in tithes. ומקבל לאו כחוקר דמי, U'mikabbel
lav k'hokher dami,
and the קבלנו kabblanu is not the same as חקירה khakira that
giving a fixed ratio is not the same as giving a fixed
amount, which makes sense to be. ומאי שדה אבותיו? U'mai sde avotav?
And when we're talking about שדה אבותיו, sde avotav, we're talking about
שדה אבותיו ממש, sde avotav mamash, that we're talking about a non-Jew
has stole land from my father and my grandfather and I'm now
כאילו ke'ilu renting it from the non-Jew
that he stole it, and so he doesn't really own it. שדה
אבותיו ממש, Sde avotav mamash, לדידי הוא דקנסו רבנן, l'didi hu d'kansu
Rabbanan, and it's only really me because I'm dealing with my father's
land that there's a special דרבנן d'Rabbanan
obligation of tithing this produce. דאיידי דחביבא ליה d'ayadei d'haviva lei that
there's like they're fining me,
they're fining me.
Really there should be no חיוב hiyyuv in מעשר ma'asser on this
land.
It's a קנס, k'nas, so there's a sort of fine.
But that seems a little unfair, fining me because someone else stole
it? Why am I suffering? Yes, why?
טפי ואזיל ומקבל לה, Tapi v'azei u'mikabbel lah, אבל איניש דעלמא לא,
Aval inish d'alma lo, because I will actually do it. ולדידי מאי
טעמא קנסו? U'l'didi mai ta'ama kansu? Why only for me, קנסו רבנן?
kansu Rabbanan? אמר רבי יוחנן כדי שתהא ברה בידו Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
k'dei she'tehei barah b'yado because I want, we want me, where it's
my ancestral land, we want me to go buy it back. We
want it to be nice and fixed for me.
If it was somebody else's land, then they wouldn't have to do
no one else would actually follow this rule.
No, meaning then I wouldn't have to take מעשר ma'asser if it
was somebody else's land.
Right, but I also wouldn't rent that land and so it would
just end up in the hand of a non-Jew when we want
the Jew to go buy the land back.
That's what I'm saying. So if you, you know, if some non-Jew,
whatever it is, stole someone else's land, so your land, and I'm
on it, and I get it from him, then I don't have
to
give מעשר.
ma'asser. כאילו. Ke'ilu. לכאורה. Likhora. Okay. אמר רב ירמיה, Amar Rav Yirmiya,
yeah, can
you just explain
whose ancestral land was this?
If I have my plot of I don't, I'm a לוי. Levi.
So if somebody else from another שבט shevet has
ancestral land that they were given in the whatever the חילוק הארץ,
khiluk ha-aretz, and a non-Jew has come and occupied it.
Okay, I got it. So he's, this fellow is renting, leasing, whatever
he's doing, as a second from this non-Jew. Yes. His own ancestral
land? Right. But could it be the ancestral land of the person
who's doing the שבט? shevet? That's what we're talking about. And so
there's a...
Which is this is a complicated סוגיא sugya and you'll see and
there are different interpretations of what it's actually talking about. So but
it's too much to do and it's already a clock we have
to go further with this. Okay. So it's not actually doing it
because of the change. He's taking the מעשר maser because it's his
actual ancestral land. Right. Not because it has anything
to do with the change really, right? Not... yeah. Something like that.
Okay, to go on though we have the same response of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says כדי שישפה בידו kedei sheyishpeh beyado that we
have a special
דין דרבנן din d'rabbanan for this person so that he'll buy it
back. And רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah comes again and says כגון דא
צריכה רבה. kegon da tzaricha rabba. For explanation like this you need
a master because wouldn't have thought of it otherwise. איתמר, Itmar, a
new thing entirely. היורד לתוך שדה חבירו ונטעה שלא ברשות. Hayored letoch
sdei chaveiro unata'ah shelo birshut. I go into my neighbor's yard and
I plant a tree. I don't know why I'm doing that, it
seems strange to me but apparently that's what we're talking about. Garda
at my own? אמר רב, Amar Rav, שמין לו וידו על התחתונה.
shamin lo veyado al hatachtona. We figure out how much it first
we evaluate what this is worth. So that's both evaluating the added
value to the land and we evaluate the amount that it would
have cost to do it, the הוצאות. hotza'ot. So the labor is,
you know, asset plus labor. Asset or labor, וידו על התחתונה, veyado
al hatachtona, so you give get one of them. You get the
lesser amount because you did this ridiculous thing where you went into
somebody else's field and put a tree
there where he didn't want it.
So it's worth the lesser of the value or the labor. Either
the labor or the value that it adds, the lesser of those,
וידו על התחתונה veyado al hatachtona because you did something dumb.
ושמואל אמר אומדין כמה אדם רוצה ליתן בשדה
זו לינטעה,
uShmuel amar omdin kama adam rotze litten
besadeh zo linto'ah, right?
If let's say it's... No, I think it's the other person's. שמואל
Shmuel says no, we actually evaluate how much אדם adam how much
a person would pay to have
this שדה לינטעה sadeh linto'ah to לינטעה. lintotah.
How much would I pay to have somebody come and plant the
field? So it's one specific thing, it's not וידו על התחתונה, yado
al hatachtona, there's one rule. Okay. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa,
ולא פליגי. velo pligi. There's actually no there's actually no disagreement between
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel even though it looks like looks like
it. כאן בשדה העשויה לינטע. Kan besadeh ha'asuyah litta. So the שמואל's
Shmuel position is about a שדה sadeh that it should be planted
anyway. כאן בשדה שאינה עשויה לינטע. Kan besadeh she'einah asuyah litta. And
רב's Rav position is about one that's not actually meant to plant
trees and I wanted it for grain. הא דרב Ha d'Rav לאו
בפירוש איתמר אלא מכללא איתמר. lav beferush itmar ela mikhalla itmar. This
comes up a few times where we have a מחלוקת machloket רב
ושמואל Rav veShmuel where there isn't really a מחלוקת machloket רב ושמואל
Rav veShmuel and רב Rav didn't really say what he said. He
said there's another story about רב Rav and so we deduce the
basic statement from the מעשה. ma'aseh. מכללא איתמר, Mikhalla itmar, we learn
it from somewhere else. דההוא דאתא לקמיה דרב, D'hahu d'ata lekamei deRav,
somebody came before רב Rav having done this, having had this situation
where he planted a tree in his neighbor's field or the neighbor
had a tree planted in his field without his permission. אמר ליה
זיל שום ליה Amar lei zil shum lei evaluate it. אמר ליה
לא בעינא, Amar lei lo ba'ina, I don't want it in my
field, he says. It's not just that there is and I want
to know how much I have to pay this person for it
because it's nice, it's that I don't want it here and I
need to know how much to pay him to get rid of
it. אמר ליה זיל שום ליה וידו על התחתונה. Amar lei zil
shum lei veyado al hatachtona. Ah okay, you don't want it, so
you have to pay him the lesser amount of the two, the
הוצאות hotza'ot or the שבח, shvach, the amount that it would have
cost him to do it and the amount that it adds to
your land. אמר ליה לא בעינא, Amar lei lo ba'ina, I don't
want it. ובסוף חזי דגדרה וקא מנטר לה, Ubesof chazi degadra veloka
mantarta lei, but in the end they see that the guy actually
fenced in the field and is guarding it. So he does want
it, so he was lying or he changed his mind. אמר ליה
גלית אדעתך דניחא לך, Amar lei galita ada'atcha denicha lach, it's clear
to me that you want it because you put a fence around
your field, around your nice new olive tree. זיל שום ליה וידו
על העליונה. Zil shum lei veyado al ha'elyona. No, now you have
to go by the other position that when you want it, I
hold like שמואל Shmuel that his that he gets the higher amount
or I hold that he gets the higher amount. איתמר, Itmar, another
thing, another idea. Now we're not going to talk about the trees,
we're going to talk about building a building on in your property.
היורד לתוך חורבתו של חבירו ובנאה שלא ברשותו. Hayored letoch churbato shel
chaveiro uvana'ah shelo birshuto. I go into somebody else's ruin and I
build I rebuild the building without your permission, שלא ברשותו. shelo birshuto.
ואמר לו עצי ואבני אני נוטל, Ve'amar lo atai ve'avnai inna naseiva,
but I changed my mind. I didn't want to build that building
anymore, I want my stones and my wood back. רב נחמן אומר,
Rav Nachman omer, remember we had this come up earlier, what happens
if I want to I change my mind about putting it there
or you don't want it there. שמין לו. Shamin lo. When I
went and did this strange thing where I built a building without
your permission and then I say I want the materials back, you're
allowed to take your materials back, says רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. רב
ששת אמר אין שמין לו. Rav Sheshet amar ein shamin lo. No,
we don't listen to him. מתיבי רבי שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Mativei
Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel omer, בית שמאי אומרים שמין לו ובית הלל
אומרים אין שמין לו. Beit Shammai omerim shamin lo uBeit Hillel omerim
ein shamin lo. לימא רב נחמן דאמר כבית שמאי. Leima Rav Nachman
d'amar keBeit Shammai. It looks like there's a problem with רב נחמן's
Rav Nachman opinion because he holds like בית שמאי Beit Shammai and
we don't פסקן pasken like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. הוא דאמר כי
האי תנא, Hu d'amar kihai tanna, he doesn't hold like that version
of the מחלוקת בית הלל ובית שמאי, machloket Beit Hillel uBeit Shammai,
he holds like this version of the מחלוקת בית הלל ובית שמאי.
machloket Beit Hillel uBeit Shammai. דתניא, D'tanya, as it's taught. דתניא שומעין
לו דברי רבי שמעון בן אלעזר. Detanya shomin lo divrei Rabi Shimon
ben Elazar. He holds like רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabi Shimon ben
Elazar that everybody agrees שומעין לו. shomin lo. Everybody agrees that we
listen to him when he wants to take his materials back after
building in the other person's ruin without his permission. רבי שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabi Shimon ben Gamliel is the one who holds that בית
הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai disagree about it. בית
שמאי אומרים שומעין לו ובית הלל אומרים אין שומעין לו. Beit Shammai
omrim shomin lo u'Beit Hillel omrim ein shomin lo. מאי הוי עלה?
Mai havi ala? So what's the rule? רבי יעקב אמר רבי יוחנן,
Rabi Yakov amar Rabi Yochanan, רבי יעקב Rabi Yakov says רבי יוחנן,
Rabi Yochanan, בבית שומעין לו. be'bayit shomin lo. Okay we hold like
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר's Rabi Shimon ben Elazar version of the מחלוקת
machloket בית הלל בית שמאי Beit Hillel Beit Shammai that there isn't
one. And so we hold like רב נחמן Rav Nachman that with
regard to a house that was a building that was built in
somebody else's ruin that I can take back my materials if I
feel like it. ובשדה u'visadeh but when we're talking about a tree
that was planted in a field, אין שומעין לו. ein shomin lo.
מאי טעמא? Mai tama? Why is there a different rule for a
field? משום יישוב ארץ ישראל mishum yishuv Eretz Yisrael because we like
to have trees in the land of Israel. איכא דאמרי משום כחש
דארעא Ika d'amri mishum kachsha d'ara because you're actually doing bad things
to the field when you do that. מאי בינייהו? Mai beineihu? איכא
בינייהו חוץ לארץ. Ika beineihu chutz l'aretz. What's the difference between the
two reasons? Whether the rule applies outside of Israel. If the only
reason that אין שומעין לו ein shomin lo is because of יישוב
ארץ ישראל, yishuv Eretz Yisrael, if the only reason that we don't
let you take back your plant is because we want the land
of Israel to be built up, then we would let you take
back your plant outside of the land of Israel. If it's because
of damage that you did to the field, then the rule should
be the same whether inside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or not.
Now we have a new משנה. Mishna. המשכיר בית לחבירו בימות הגשמים
אינו יכול להוציאו מן החג ועד הפסח בימות החמה שלשים יום. Hamaskir
bayit l'chavero bi'ymot hageshamim eino yachol l'hotzio min hachag v'ad hapesach bi'ymot
hachama shloshim yom. If I rent, somebody rents to me a house
in the winter. רש״י Rashi and רמב״ם Rambam agree that this is
I rent it without any amount of time, and the rule would
be different if we gave a fixed amount of time. Then if
it's in the winter from any time from סוכות Sukkot until פסח,
Pesach, I can't kick you out, that you get to stay there
for the entire however many months that is, six months, something like
that. Yeah. אינו יכול להוציאו מן החג ועד הפסח בימות החמה Eino
yachol l'hotzio min hachag v'ad hapesach bi'ymot hachama but if it's in
the summer after פסח, Pesach, שלשים יום, shloshim yom, I can kick
you out after a month. ובכרכים uv'krachim but if we're dealing with
the towns, אחד ימות החמה ואחד ימות הגשמים שנים עשר חודש. echad
yemot hachama v'echad yemot hageshamim shneim asar chodesh. I have an entire
year to live there whatever season I'm in. ובחנויות uv'chanuyot but if
we're speaking about stalls in the market, אחד עיירות ואחד כרכים, echad
ayarot v'echad krachim, no matter what sort of town I'm in, שנים
עשר חודש, shneim asar chodesh, I also get a year. רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר חנות של נחתומים ושל צבעים שלש שנים. Raban Shimon
ben Gamliel omer chanut shel nachtumim v'shel tzavaim shalosh shanim. The baker
and the dyer get three years. And why? We'll deal with the
end of this גמרא. Gemara. מאי שנא ימות הגשמים Mai shna yemot
hageshamim says the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara asks the basic question,
what are we talking about ימות הגשמים yemot hageshamim for? Why is
it different between whether I'm renting in the summer or renting in
the winter? דכי אגר איניש ביתא בימות הגשמים אגר לכולהו ימות הגשמים
ימות החמה נמי דכי אגר איניש ביתא לכולהו ימות החמה אגר. D'ki
agar inish beita bi'ymot hageshamim agar l'kuleihu yemot hageshamim yemot hachama nami
d'ki agar inish beita l'kuleihu yemot hachama agar. If you're telling me
that if
I'm renting a house in the winter I'm renting for the entire
winter, why is it not the same case when I rent a
house in the summer that I rent it for the entire season?
Since when do I only rent houses for a month at a
time? Anytime. אלא בימות הגשמים היינו טעמא דלא שכיח
ביתא למיגר. Ela bi'ymot hageshamim hainu ta'ama
d'lo shchiach beita l'meigar.
Ah, the reason that it's different in winter is because there aren't
really that many homes to rent, because everybody wants to live inside
in the winter and in the summer you can move around, you
can work here, you can work there. אימא סיפא, Eima seifa,
however there's a problem because in the end of the משנה Mishna
we say something different. בכרכים אחד ימות החמה ואחד ימות הגשמים שנים
עשר חודש. B'krachim echad yemot hachama v'echad yemot hageshamim shneim asar chodesh.
ואילו מאלו ליומי סתיו בימות הגשמים מפיק ליה ואמאי הא לא שכיח
ביתא למיגר? V'ilu m'eilu l'yomei stav bi'ymot hageshamim mapik leh v'amai ha
lo shchiach beita l'meigar?
Why is there in the כרכים krachim a different rule that I
get twelve months to live there no matter when I'm renting it?
And thus even when it's in the winter and there aren't houses
to rent, I can kick you out in the middle of winter,
even though we only made the deal to rent it סתם stam
without any time. What's the agar? אגר Agar is שכר. schar. אגר
Agar the root, the Aramaic root. אגר, Agar, the root, אוכר oker
or אוגר oger would
be להשכיר. l'haskir. And then also it's used sometimes אגר agar is
used as שכר schar like reward as
well.
ואמאי הא לא שכיח ביתא למיגר? V'amai ha lo shchiach beita l'meigar?
It shouldn't be the case because if I'm kicking you out in
winter, you're not going to have anywhere else to live. אמר רב
יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says no, we have
to read the משנה Mishna differently. להודיע קתני. L'hodia katani. We should
teach the משנה Mishna that it's not that you have a certain
amount of time you can't be kicked out, it's that I have
to tell you when you're going to be kicked out at a
certain time. והכי קאמר V'hachi ka'amar and this is how we read
the משנה. Mishna. המשכיר בית לחבירו סתם Hamaskir bayit l'chavero stam as
we said before, I rent you a house without saying a time
that you're going to leave, אינו יכול. eino yachol. להוציאו בימות הגשמים
מחג ועד הפסח אלא אם כן הודיעו שלשים יום מעיקרא. Lehotzio BeYemos
HaGeshamim MeChag VeAd HaPesach Ela Im Kein Hodio Shloshim Yom Meikara. I
can't kick you out during ימות הגשמים Yemos HaGeshamim in the winter
at all between סוכות Succos and פסח Pesach unless I told you
thirty days beforehand. תני נמי הכי, Tani Nami Hachi, there's also a
ברייתא. Braisa. כשאמרו שלשים KesheAmru Shloshim in the משנה Mishnah when they
said thirty days in the summer,
כשאמרו שנים עשר חודש KesheAmru Shneim Asar Chodesh and when they also
said an entire year with regard to the כרכים, Krakhim, לא אמרו
אלא להודיע. Lo Amru Ela Lehodiya. They only meant, they didn't mean
that you can't be kicked out; it means that you had to
inform him that he's going to be kicked out with that amount
of
notice. וכשם שהמשכיר צריך להודיע כך שוכר צריך להודיע, Ukeshem SheHaMaskir Tzarich
Lehodiya Kach Socher Tzarich Lehodiya, and just as continues the ברייתא Braisa
that the owner of the house that's renting it out has to
tell you "I'm going to kick you out and put somebody else
in there,"
also the renter himself has to give fair warning because otherwise he's
going to be left with property on his hands being
unused. דאמר ליה אי הודעתן הוינא מותיבנא ביה אינש מעליא,
DeAmar Lei Ei Hodatan Havina Motivna Bei
Inash Malya, had you told me that you were leaving, I would
have found somebody else and this isn't fair to me; you should
actually be staying out the entire winter. אמר רב אסי אי נכנס
יום אחד בימות הגשמים אינו יכול להוציאו מחג עד הפסח. Amar Rav
Assi Ei Nichnas Yom Echad BeYemos HaGeshamim Eino Yachol Lehotzio MeChag Ad
HaPesach. If he was there for a day, seemingly, in the winter,
אינו יכול להוציאו מחג עד הפסח. Eino Yachol Lehotzio MeChag Ad HaPesach.
והא אנן שלשים יום תנן, VeHa Anan Shloshim Yom Tenan, so why
do you talk about one day? I thought it says thirty days.
אה, הכי קאמר אי נכנס יום אחד בימות הגשמים מהני שלשים יום.
Ah, Hachi Ka'amar Ei Nichnas Yom Echad BeYemos HaGeshamim MeHanei Shloshim Yom.
This is what רב אסי Rav Assi means: If one of the
thirty days from the time I informed you was during סוכות Succos
or during, that is, it was in the winter, מהני שלשים יום,
MeHanei Shloshim Yom,
I can't kick you out. I have to inform you at latest
on the 15th of אלול Elul
so that the entire period of הודעה Hoda'ah that I'm going to
kick you out is within ימות החמה, Yemos HaChama, is during the
summer, and so you leave at סוכות. Succos.
If I informed you on the last day of אלול Elul and
oh, the 30th of תשרי Tishrei comes, it's ימות הגשמים, Yemos HaGeshamim,
you can't kick me out. Sorry, I'm here until פסח. Pesach.
Okay. אמר רב הונא ואי בא לרבויי בדמיה מרבה. Amar Rav Huna
VeEi Ba Leribuyei BeDamei Marbeh. And but I can,
however, I can increase the price of your rent because you're allowed
to stay here as long as you want, but I can charge
you more for it.
Really? אמר ליה רב נחמן האי דנקיט
בחושיה דלא שבקיה לגלימא. Amar Lei Rav Nachman Hai DeNakit BeChushyei DeLo
Shavkeih LeGlima. But that means that I'm holding you by somewhere where
I wouldn't normally grab you
in terms of a man. We're literally, it's a euphemism for testicles.
I'm grabbing you by them and I'm telling you to give me
your coat. So really, it's like you're stuck here because you would
have to tell me ahead of time. You're allowed to stay here
and I can charge as much as I want? That doesn't make
any sense. That's not fair.
לא צריכא דאוקיר בתי. Lo Tzericha DeOkir Batei. No, we're only talking
about a case where houses in general became more expensive. I don't
have to go with the original price we determined. If prices go
up, I can charge you normal market value. פשיטא נפלה ליה ביתא.
Pshita
Nafla Lei Beita. Oh,
sorry, that's not פשיטא, Pshita, that's a different kind of פשיטא. Pshita.
פשיטא נפלה ליה ביתא. Pshita Nafla Lei Beita. אמר ליה לא עדיפת
מינאי. Amar Lei Lo Adifat Minai.
If I, the owner of this house that I'm renting out, if
my own house that I'm living in falls apart, I can kick
you out of the house you're renting because לא עדיפת מינאי. Lo
Adifat Minai. You're not better than me. I don't have a house
to stay in and I own this one. Leave.
Sounds relevant to our code of today.
לא עדיפת מינאי. Lo Adifat Minai. זבניה או ארתיה או יהביה במתנה.
Zavneh O Arteih O Yahveih BeMatana.
If I sell it or I give it or I rent it,
if I sell it or I give it as a gift, אמר
ליה לא עדיפת מגברא דאתית מיניה. Amar Lei Lo Adifat MiGavra DeAtis
Mineih.
If I the owner
sold the rented house to somebody else or I gave it to
somebody else and the second, the new owner wants to kick me
out, I say, "You can't kick me out just like that guy
couldn't kick me out. You bought a house to rent. I'm renting
it. I'll pay you your
rent." However, so those are the two פשיטא Pshita cases. כללא לבריה
חזינן. Klala LeVreih Chazinan. But if I'm going to give it as
a gift to my son when he gets married,
חזינן, Chazinan, we have to determine what the case is. אי הוה
אפשר לאודועיה, Ei Hava Efshar Le'odoyei, if it was possible for me
to tell you, oh by the way in a month this is
going to be my son's house, you're going to have to vacate,
איבעי ליה לאודועיה, Iba'ei Lei Le'odoyei,
then he has to say that. ואי לא, VeEi Lo, אמר ליה
לא עדיפת מינאי. Amar Lei Lo Adifat Minai. But if I couldn't
tell, for instance, my son got engaged and the father of the
bride doesn't want to wait at all, they want to have a
wedding right now (this is רש"י's Rashi explanation, he literally says this),
then I can kick you out of the house because I need
to give it to my son. לא עדיפת מינאי, Lo Adifat Minai,
you are not better than I. ההוא גברא דזבן ארבע דחמרא, Hahu
Gavra DeZavan Arba DeChamra,
I have a ship full of wine. This is a very interesting
story. לא
אשכח דוכתא לאותוביה, Lo Ashkach Duchta LeOtoveih, but I don't have a
place to put it. I don't have a place to put my
wine. אמרי לה ההיא איתתא, Amrei lah ha-i itteta, but I say
a woman, I say to a woman, אית לך דוכתא לאגורי, it
lakh dukhta le-aguri, do you have a place to rent to me
so I can put this wine there? אמרה ליה לא. Amra leh
lo. No. No, I don't have any space. אזל
קדשה, Azal kadshe, he says okay, do you want to get married?
And she says okay. יהבה ליה דוכתא לעייולי, Yehaba lei dukhta le-aylei,
לעייולי, le-aylei, and then she gives him a place because they, because
they're married. אזל לביתיה, Azal le-veiteih, כתב לה גיטא, katav lah gitta,
שדר
לה, shadar lah, אתא איהי, ata ihi,
אתא איהי, ata ihi, okay so then he says okay now I
have a place to put my wine, now I have to get
divorced. So he goes home, he writes a get, he sends it
to her. Not a very nice person, he's a truly terrible person.
אתא איהי אגר שקולי מניה וביה ואפיקיה ואותביה בשבילא, Ata ihi agar
shakulie minei-u-bei ve-afikei ve-otevei bi-shvila, and she says okay, she hires some
guys, she takes the wine and she puts it in the street.
אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehoshua,
which seems unfair. It seems like he rented a space from her
כאילו, ke-ilu, and so she should have to leave it there because
he rented space from her. She's, why should she have to do
that? She gave it to him only because they were married. But
we'll see that that's exactly what comes out. אמר רב
הונא
בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehoshua, the case comes
before רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yehoshua, כאשר
עשה כן יעשה לו גמולו ישוב בראשו. ka-asher asah kein ye-aseh lo,
gemulo yashuv bi-rosho. That he was unfair to her and she can
be unfair to him.
לא מיבעיא חצר דלא קיימא לאגרא אלא אפילו חצר דקיימא לאגרא. Lo
miba-ei khatzer de-lo ka-ima le-agra, ela afilu khatzer de-ka-ima le-agra. And it
doesn't matter whether we're talking about whether she really did have a
place to rent or whether she didn't have a place to rent
and now it's just in her house because she has to because
they were married.
And it would be really terrible not to. אמרה ליה לכולי עלמא
ניחא לי לאוגורי ולך לא ניחא לי דדמית עלי כי אריה ארבא.
Amar lei le-khulei alma nika li le-ogurei u-lakh lo nika li, de-damit
alai ki-aryah arva.
I would have rented to anybody else, I didn't really want to
rent to you because you're because you're like a lion and I
don't like you. And so apparently they got married. Anyway, the point
is is that there are cases in which in which case the
rights to renting don't apply. רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, now we're going
back to the Mishna. שלחן של נחתומים ושל צבעים שלש שנים. Shulchan
shel naktomim ve-shel tzava'im shalosh shanim. That you get three years to
rent a חנות, chanat, a stall of a baker or the bread
seller really, and of dyers. Why? תנא מפני שקיפן מרובה Tana mipnei
she-kifan merubeh because there's a takes a lot of credit to do
them and you have much longer you rent for longer periods.
I think that actually like applies in stores in general today that
it's like you don't rent a store on a short contract but
there are people who will rent houses on short contracts though there
are pop-up stores which have shorter contracts. Doesn't matter. Okay, I think
we're going to do the Mishna quickly.
המשכיר בית לחבירו
המשכיר חייב בדלת בנגר ובמנעול.
Ha-maskir bayit
le-chavero, ha-maskir chayav ba-delet, ba-nagar u-va-man'ul. If I rent a house to
somebody else, I have to put in a door and an inside
lock and an outside lock.
ובכל דבר שמעשה אומן U-ve-chol davar she-ma'aseh uman ובכל דבר שמעשה אומן,
U-ve-chol davar she-ma'aseh uman, and anything that requires a craftsman to produce.
אבל דבר שאינו מעשה אומן השוכר עושהו. Aval davar she-eino ma'aseh uman,
ha-socher oseh-hu.
Anything that isn't a מעשה אומן, ma'aseh uman, anything that isn't a
craftsman's product but is a normal person's product, the renter has to
produce themselves.
That would be things like bed and what?
Yeah, we're going to see it gives examples. הזבל שבחצר, Ha-zevel she-ba-chatzer,
any manure that's found in the backyard is belongs to the owner
of the house. ואין לשוכר אלא היוצא מן התנור ומן הכירה בלבד.
Ve-ein la-socher ela ha-yotzei min ha-tanur u-min ha-kirayim bilvad. And these but
the renter only has rights to what came out of the oven
and the double stove. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. המשכיר בית לחבירו, Ha-maskir
bayit le-chavero, we have a braita that says similar rules or expands
on the mishna. המשכיר בית לחבירו המשכיר
חייב להעמיד לו דלתות,
Ha-maskir bayit
le-chavero, ha-maskir chayav le-ha'amid lo daltot, you have to put in doors
like we saw. וחלונות, Ve-chalonot, he has to put in windows. וחזק
את התקרה, Ve-chazek et ha-tikrah, he has to fix the roof. לסמוך
לו קורה, Lismoch lo korah, he has to put in a beam.
והשוכר חייב לעשות לו סולם, U-va-socher chayav la'asot lo sulam, he has
to build a, he has to have his own ladder to go
up to the roof. ולעשות לו מעקה, Vela'asot lo ma'akeh, to put
on the thing, the fence around the roof. ולעשות לו מרזב, Vela'asot
lo marzev, which is a gutter of some sort. ולטוח את גגו,
Velatiah et gago, and to thatch the roof when necessary. בעו, Ba'u,
which is today not,
today I think is more מעשה אומן. ma'aseh uman. בעו מיניה מרב
ששת, Ba'u minei Rav Sheshet, מזוזה על מי? mezuzah al mi? Who
is chayav on
the mezuzah? אמר רב משרשיא מזוזה חובת הדר היא. Amar Rav Mesharsheya
mezuzah chovat ha-dar hu. For רב משרשיא Rav Mesharsheya said explicitly that
the mezuzah is the obligation of the person who's living there to
put up.
אלא מקום מזוזה על מי? Ela mekom mezuzah al mi? But the
place of the mezuzah, the actual piece of material that goes on
the doorpost where the mezuzah has to go, who's chayav to put
that there properly?
אמר להו רב ששת תניתוה דבר שאין מעשה אומן השוכר עושהו והאי
נמי לאו. Amar le-hu Rav Sheshet Tenitu-ha, davar she-ein ma'aseh uman ha-socher
oseh-hu, ve-hai nami lav. And this is not.
מעשה אומן הוא אפשר הוא בגופתא דתניא. Ma'aseh uman hu, efshar hu
bi-gufta de-tanya.
I don't get this.
No, I think we'll stop here
in
the middle of a thing.
Very good. Okay.